[Music]
Jordan it's great to to interview you
again I need you back in October last
year and then made I've now made two
documentaries about you and a big focus
for rebel wisdom is kind of making sense
of the cultural moment and making sense
of your success and whatever it presents
and I don't know if you remember but the
very first question I asked you back in
October and the interview was firstly
what you make of your success so far and
are you ready for it to continue because
I had I had a sense back then that what
your message represented was something
the culture desperately needed the sort
of and what that signifies to me is a
kind of reintegration of a sacred did
you have any sense back then the the
exponential success that you were going
to have between then and now well I mean
the most likely outcome at each of the
what would you say at each point where I
might notice what's going on around me
has been that this was stalled but it
isn't stopping so I've been thinking
about that pretty much non-stop I would
say and I have some some solutions let's
say or some ideas that I didn't present
in October so one of the things I've
realized is that part of what's pushing
part of what's accounting for this the
popularity of my ideas is actually a
secondary consequence of a technological
revolution and I've seen that more
clearly since October
partly because I can see the mainstream
media dying at a faster and faster rate
and the alternative media expanding
faster and faster so television radio
and the classic print media had shared
one thing in common which was a extreme
restriction in bandwidth this was
especially true of television because
each minute of television given the
necessity to broadcast and the expense
that was unbelievably expensive and so
there just wasn't time to do anything on
television
there's no time and so if you had
something important to say or even
something unimportant for that matter
most of the time it had to be compressed
into something approximating 30 seconds
which wouldn't even be your words it
would be a journalist common commenting
on what you said and if you were really
pushing the envelope maybe you'd have 25
minutes on a talk show that was devoted
to your ideas but then even that would
be highly scripted and so television
made people look stupider than they were
even to the producers of television
because of this narrow bandwidth the the
rise of video online and audio as well
has blown the bandwidth limitation out
of our mass communication and it turns
out that people are smarter with longer
attention spans than we thought what
happened with me was that for one reason
or another I was an early adopter of
that technology and so there's this
massive technological transformation
which is a Gutenberg revolution in the
provision of video and audio no barrier
to production because it doesn't cost
anything anyone can do it people can
communicate with it you can cut up
YouTube videos you can make your
documentaries the entry point is easy
audio podcasts and that sort of thing
which can be of indefinite length allow
people to use found time to listen more
people can listen than can read like all
of these things add up to a massive
technological revolution and it's that
upswell in technology that in part has
propelled what I've been doing to
tu-tu-tu-tu-tu-tu this mass audience and
so that's been a relief to figure that
out because it depersonalized is it to
some degree right and so I used the
metaphor when I've been asked about this
before of being on a wave
I'm surfing on a giant wave but the wave
isn't something that I've done it's part
of this technological revolution so
that's a relief to know that and I'm
quite convinced that that's the case
because there are other people who are
occupying the same space essentially Joe
Rogan is a very good example of that and
the various commentators on on YouTube
who've become increasingly influential
and powerful same thing driven by the
technology they happen to be early
adopters and so and then there's a
secondary question which is well is
there anything specific in relationship
to my content let's say and I would say
also that is a the case and I think what
I've been able to do with reasonable
effectiveness is to draw a conceptual
equation equivalence between the meaning
that's necessary to sustain you in life
given its suffering and malevolence and
the necessity to adopt responsibility
and I think there's something new about
that I mean I don't know how new I'm
sure I am NOT the first person who's
discovered that but I think I've done a
reasonable job of pointing out to people
that that the suffering that's intrinsic
to life in the absence of meaning is not
tolerable it it it destroys and corrupts
and that the proper pathway out of that
isn't rights or happiness or entitlement
or or anything that's associated with
with with individual ease let's say but
with the adoption of something
approximating maximal responsibility and
people get that like it's it's not that
hard to understand when it's laid out
like that and lots of people especially
young people especially people who are
young and also somewhat nihilistic in
their orientation perhaps because of an
excess of intellectual criticism or they
grab that immediately think oh there's
the missing piece I see it's that the
the antidote to this meaninglessness
this void that I'm for
isn't hedonism it's not right it's not
impulsive pleasure it's none of that
it's responsibility it's like oh yes
okay that everything snaps into place
and so that's been I think that's the
most essential part of the message to
the degree that what I'm doing has an
essential message that would be it and I
do think that's what it counts for a
large part of its impact and you
mentioned Joe Rogan before and you and
here group together in this sort of new
constellation of the intellectual dark
web what do you see is the I mean what
you make of your kind of inclusion in
this and what do you see is its role
going forward in the culture well well
it's it's it's it's like a herd of cats
right because so I've thought about well
what what what unites us to the degree
that there's an us because that's not so
self-evident there's enough of an ask so
that the name emerged and it's stuck so
so there's something in common because
otherwise the name wouldn't have stuck
right you can't name nothing it doesn't
work and I've talked a fair bit about
this with Dave Rubin because Dave Rubin
and I have been touring together right
he opens my my discussions and adds a
nice comedic touch to them and so what
do we have in common everybody in the
group is an independent practitioner so
an entrepreneur essentially with their
own media enterprise that's autonomous
none of us are serving any master except
the audience so so and and we're all
somewhat independent financially as a
consequence of that and so that makes us
beholden to no master all of us are
engaged in these long-form discussions
right and one of the consequences of
being engaged in a long-form discussion
is that you can assume that your
intelligence that your audience is
intelligent and so that's another thing
that unites everybody in the group is we
all assume that our audience is
intelligent but I think that that's not
so much a consequence of any
particular moral virtue on our parts but
an observation that the technology has
made possible it's like oh when you can
see this I would say particularly with
Roman because in some sense he's a
trailblazer in this domain it's like Oh
turns out my audience will listen to the
three-hour discussion but he wouldn't
have been able to discover that without
the technology right so now to his
credit he was smart enough to discover
it and smart enough to notice it when he
discovered it and so and I think that
also characterizes the rest of the
people in this group it's like oh look
at that the audience actually wants our
listeners that say and viewers want
detailed in-depth unscripted spontaneous
meaningful conversation and then really
are willing to go in that direction
that's the risk-taking element like I
can give an example of that so I just
did for talks with Sam Harris who's
often grouped into this group as well on
the relationship between science and
religion say or facts and values that's
another way of thinking about it with a
bit of politics thrown in discussion of
left/right differences and so on what's
the willingness to take the risk well I
had no idea when I met Sam in Vancouver
which was where the first two of the
four talks were held I'd never met him
before we did a two podcast together one
of which was very we got locked in the
other one which was more productive I
would say but I had no idea of he had I
could talk but we we were willing to
willing to I guess that's right agreed
to take the risk to see if we could talk
in a public forum and and I think that's
another thing that characterizes the
people in that group is that they will
take those sorts of risks if you go into
a television studio a classic television
studio all the conversation is scripted
and it's actually quite frustrating
because you can't have a conversation
with the journalist because the
journalist isn't there who's there is a
frontispiece for the organization and
the organization has scripted all there
so it's not actually like talking to a
person it's really like talking to a
puppet so for better or for worse but in
these long unscripted long-form
conversations then you can take the risk
of having a conversation and that can go
spectacularly well but it can also fail
dismally so I would say those are the
things that unite us to the degree that
the group exists I mean I met when I was
in LA a week ago and about 7 of us got
together for for dinner and that was the
first time we we'd met as anything
approximating a group and you know it
was interesting to watch everybody
interact because as I said it really is
a herd of cats there's a tremendous
diversity of political opinion and a
tremendous diversity of personality like
Eric Weinstein and Joe Rogan like
they're not even members of the same
species in some ways you know so so it's
a very fractious group but I think those
things that I outlined are the elements
that basically unite it there's also
something that I sense watching some of
the discussions there's a kind of
intellectual curiosity and a sense of
people thinking in public and and
there's also a sense of maybe the
potential for people to change their
minds or to discover things during the
conversation well that's partly the
appreciation of the intelligence of the
audience it's like and I would say it is
actually the manifestation of the
process of thinking that's more
important than the conclusions that are
generated even in these discussions that
I've been having with Harris like we are
trying to to argue out to different
viewpoints because Harris believes that
values can be derived with with with
unerring precision in some sense using
the proper methodology from facts and I
I believe that it's more complicated
than that that there has to be
intermediating structures and those are
really narrative and in their nature so
there's a technical argument as well as
a variety of sub arguments of
the relative role of traditional
religion and so forth but the outcome of
the debate about those issues is partly
what people are coming to the talks to
see to to to determine what should the
conclusions be but a much larger part
perhaps is to in to observe and engage
at least by proxy in the process of
dialogue and that's more important
because dialogue is the process by which
complex problems are solved which is
what makes me a free speech advocate
fundamentally well it's not an advocate
it's like I realized that that the
protection for free speech is protection
of the mechanism whereby complex social
problems are solved and were were the
people in this group and many other
people as well are acting out that
dialogical process and and people are
happy about that as they should be and I
read The Spectator review of your recent
conversation I think you've now come to
the end of your debate for sam harris
and they said that you expressed a
little bit of irritation at some of the
when Sam didn't grass some of the points
that you were making or that you didn't
fully appreciate that he'd and
understood them I also think that Sam
Harris in particular he's built a whole
kind of personality career several books
on this atheism position do you think
that he can argue in good faith from
that perspective could he turn around
and say well actually no you're right
Jordan this atheism thing is a bit no I
think he was I think he was I think he
was conducting the discussion in good
faith I actually think that what Sam is
doing is a good faith project you know
he I think there's conceptual muddiness
about it but you know his basic premise
is that we could come to an agreement
that working to reduce unnecessary
misery and suffering is a universal good
okay fair enough that seems like a
reasonable proposition I don't think
it's a proposition of fact and he claims
that it is but that doesn't matter still
it's fair enough then
and then you know that's what
proposition another proposition is it
would be really good if our systems of
value weren't founded on error and what
do we have that's not error well we have
facts we have objective facts I mean
look at the technology look at what
we've done with our science it's like
you do want to underestimate the utility
of objective facts so maybe we can
ground the value structure in the facts
it's like well that would be good if we
could do it so and and so and then his
his ethic let's say is an amalgam of
those two propositions and I think that
his project is honorable and and and I
think he's committed to it
he also rightly is concerned with the
dangers of the Fundamentalist dangers of
revealed truth and so is very skeptical
about about the axiomatic claims of of
dogmatic religion yeah fair enough but
his the mechanisms that he outlines to
derive values from facts are
insufficient in my estimation I don't
think that his argument is sufficiently
sophisticated even though I don't doubt
it's I don't think that Sam is any less
committed to an ethical good it's not
obvious to me that he is than I am you
know and he's argued and discussed fully
in good faith as far as I'm concerned
you know with the with the odd error
because no one is negotiating 100% all
the time in good faith I mean that's a
standard that no one can can this can
achieve but I think the discussions have
been unbelievably productive and and
we'll see that certainly the crowds are
responding I don't think the crowds
would have been engaged if Sam wouldn't
be wouldn't been discussing in good
faith you know because the engagement is
actually an indication that a good faith
discussion is is occurring otherwise it
gets dull very very rapidly we'll see
what happens when the videos are
released and that'll be in August once
there the sound is edited and all
that and and then people will have a
public debate about how it how the
discussion proceeded I also think that
each discussion built on the previous
one and that we both ended up I think we
both ended that more informed and more
articulate then we started out so that's
a good that's a really good thing I
certainly understand his arguments much
better than I did well a year ago let's
say and I've heard Eric Weinstein
described sort of the cultural moment as
a kind of civil war within the left sort
of extreme left and then the sort of
moderate soft left which are probably
sort of the at least the dominating kind
of paradigm in the media I I'm I've got
a lot of progressive friends and what I
see happening recently maybe in the last
couple of weeks is a lot of them
starting to grapple with your ideas and
looking at lasting this question what
can the left learn from jordan peterson
which is which is a pretty new
development because i saw a lot of kind
of reactivity to it before how can you
personally contribute to that debate and
debate you're interesting oh yeah
absolutely
no no doubt about it no doubt about it
what one thing that i've been doing in
my tour repeatedly when i talked about
the first chapter of my book which is
stand up straight with your shoulders
back it's a discussion of hierarchies
and and their eternal nature right
because my claim is is not my claim i
think its mere fact that organisms that
have to cooperate and compete with other
organisms of their type inevitably
arrange themselves into hierarchies and
that's been going on for so long which
is at least 300 million years that our
nervous systems have adapted to
hierarchies as if there are permanent
element of being right more permanent
than trees like seriously permanent at
the most fundamental neurochemical the
one that regulates the entire brain
serotonin is acutely sensitive to
hierarchical distinctions and so that's
part of the
is it so the reason I laid that
proposition forward was to say whatever
pitfalls hierarchies might produce you
cannot lay them at the feet of the West
patriarchy or capitalism it's like
that's a non-starter you're wrong and
not just a little bit wrong
you're so seriously wrong that if you
insist upon doing that you won't even
achieve your own aims because you're
actually not grappling with the problem
the problem is if hierarchies are a
problem which they are the problem is
way more serious than mere capitalism
it's way deeper and if you're actually
interested in rectifying the constantly
the negative consequences of hierarchies
then you're going to have to get a lot
more sophisticated than there then your
idiot Marxism so so so part of the
elaboration of that argument is well
hierarchies are inevitable because we
have to solve complex problems and we
have to solve them socially and when you
implement a solution to a complex
problem socially you produce a hierarchy
because some people are better at the
implementation than others so there's a
hierarchy of competence and then there's
a hierarchy of distribution of the
Spoils and so and in both of those
hierarchies you get a disproportionate
clumping of resources at the top and
dispossession at the bottom in the
nature of hierarchies so what's the left
for the left is to remind those who are
benefiting from the hierarchies that the
hierarchy comes at a cost and the cost
is the clumping of people at the bottom
and that that's an eternal cost and it's
not trivial and so that's what the left
should be properly focused on the Left
should be providing the voice of those
who are dispossessed by hierarchies and
the right should be saying yeah but the
damn hierarchies are necessary and
they're not only necessary but they're
also productive than the left says yes
but they tilt towards tyranny and they
can be occupied inappropriately by
people who are playing games of power
fair enough the right has to take that
into account the hierarchy can
rigidify and is likely to do that and it
can be taken over by people who are
corrupt and that's likely to happen and
so but but it's okay because the dialog
could work out the the right could say
well yeah we need the damn hierarchies
and they need to be but wrists and the
left can say yes but they have to be
maintained properly so they don't
deteriorate and degenerate and and I
think that's I think that's ancient
wisdom I think the ancient Egyptians had
figured that out in their symbolic
representations so now when the left
goes too far
it does something like say well how
about no hierarchies it's like no how
about not wrong because all that happens
if you flatten one of the things that
happens if you flatten out the hierarchy
is that you can't even organize your
perceptions you can't perceive the world
without looking at the world through a
hierarchy of value and if because you
can't perceive the world unless you make
one thing more important than all the
other things because you don't even know
what to look at and if one thing isn't
more important than all the other things
then you have nothing to aim at if you
have nothing to aim at then you have no
meaning in your life so the left can't
just demolish the hierarchies in the
name of some equality of outcome let's
say because you blow out the future you
leave people aimless and you destroyed
the very institutions that allow people
to make competent progress in the world
that's not an acceptable outcome so we
have to we have to agree to live with
the tension necessity for hierarchies
the proclivity for them to pathologize
and the the necessary voice of the left
and speaking for thee for the
dispossessed so and I mean I've as far
as I'm concerned I've said something
approximating that through my entire
career and so the fact that the left
wingers have been irritated at me is
well in some sense that's an inevitable
consequence of me taking on the radical
left wingers but it's also the refusal
by the moderate left to deal with their
internal problems and the sticking point
that I hear a lot from my sort of more
progressive friends is
you're sort of primary focus is on the
individual yeah well that's that's too
bad for them because the primary should
be you know I can agree with that but
what I the the paradox that they would
say it's like okay focus on the
individual but you have to accept that
there are some situations that are much
more conducive to an individual thriving
than other situations so their focus on
structural inequality you're focusing on
the individual is there not some
interplay between most definitely well
obviously because people do have group
identities the question is whether
whether the group or the individual
identity should be paramount and the
left distance the radical leftist answer
is well there is the look it's not me
that's failing to take into account
those two levels of analysis it's the
bloody radical leftist because for them
it's the collective and that's that and
so it's obvious as far as I'm concerned
that people have their individuality and
then behind that they have their they
have their group like multiple group
identities which is also a big problem
but also poverty or any of these
situations that make it much more
difficult for people to self actualize
well what I think they'd argue is they
don't hear you talk about that very much
well it isn't first of all it's not
self-evident like I'm not
I don't accept Maslow's hierarchy of
needs I don't think it's necessarily
more difficult for people who are poor
to self-actualize
sorry I don't buy that he's because what
that would mean think about what that
would mean that would mean that the rich
are morally superior that's what that
means because they have all the
opportunities to self actualize so
obviously if the material conditions are
the prerequisite for self-actualization
then the rich are morally superior to
the poor is that really an argument we
want to make and then in fact I don't
think that that's even even vaguely
reasonable because one of the things
that does help build character is
privation
now obviously starving to death is an an
excess of privation
so there are limit conditions but the
it's a leftist trope that the provision
of additional material resources will
produce ethically superior human beings
sorry
not true
and in fact sometimes quite the contrary
so so so I don't I don't I don't buy
that argument in the least I also think
that under most circumstances in
accepting those of exceptional privation
and even perhaps under those conditions
in most is in most cases your best bet
to move people forward is to concentrate
on the development of their individual
character and their individual their
individual moral character fund because
moral character is actually your moral
character is actually the set of tools
that you have to operate effectively in
the world because otherwise morality
would be of no utility and morality is
in some sense precisely that wit which
is of maximal utility and so and and the
other objection that I would throw it at
the radical left is how do you know that
your your emphasis on collective
existence isn't just an abdication of
your personal responsibility well of
course it's not it's like no no no
seriously here it's not that easy to add
or personal responsibility maximal
personal responsibility what makes you
think you're not running away from it
you have every reason to you really have
that stellar moral character really
that's that's your self analysis sorry I
don't buy it
and I especially don't buy it when I
look at the consequences of leftist
revolutions because all these people of
stellar moral character when they
undertake their collectivist revolution
nothing comes out of that but absolute
bloody catastrophe so so all the
well-meaning aims aside my my sense of a
lot of the progressive people that I
know is that they're not they're sort of
from a new generation they're not
generally materialist that they're sort
of very spiritually aware and I i sense
a kind of implicit message in what
you're saying that I'd never heard made
explicitly that in some sense
materialism is a deadening doctrine I
mean you look at the opioid crisis and
America you look at a lot of these if
poverty is seen as a more sort of
also also as a sort of spiritual crisis
or a spot of crisis of the soul as much
as anything else is it mostly that like
it'd be a lovely ring if if poverty was
caused by lack of money mmm we could fix
it really easily there but my point I
think is to say that if if you were
framing your message in that way I think
there would be a lot of people on the
left
who'd be receptive to that message sort
of that that actually there is a crisis
of that the crisis of already call it
like world view has real consequences
and a lot of poverty we're seeing in the
world is to do with this kind of
materialist worldview that has become
become corrupt or at least kind of
stripped all of the meaning and purpose
oh yeah well that's a good point well
right well I mean I don't believe that
materialism materialist hedonism is a
sufficient solution now it's a bit more
complicated than that because I do think
that functional democratic systems are
actually pretty good at reasonable
hedonism like I'm pretty happy that our
system produces a variety of toothpastes
and a variety of toilet papers and a
variety of sanitary napkins all of these
things that that are basically oriented
towards what would you call them
individual creature comforts there's
something about that that's really
merciful and properly egalitarian and so
a certain degree of material hedonism is
a good thing right because it's nice
that people can have their basic needs
taken care of in a dignified manner but
as a as a ultimate solution to the
problems of life its insufficient which
is again why I don't really like Abraham
Maslow's hierarchy of needs you know it
isn't it isn't a progression up the
moral chain because of the provision of
additional material resources doesn't
work that way that doesn't mean that you
don't want to you want to set up a
situation where as many people as
possible are absent the terrible
strictures of privation but we are doing
that quite rapidly thank god so so
I think we're the leftists are less
happy with what I'm doing is the case
that I'm making that the meaning that
transcends mere materialism is to be
found in the adoption of individual
responsibilities because I wouldn't say
that that's a core message certainly not
of the radical left it's not that at all
because generally they construe the
individual as either the oppressor or
the suffering oppressed but not as the
active agent as either of those active
agents the problem with the oppressor
oppress narrative is even though there's
an element of truth to it each of us can
be subdivided into so many group
identities that there's at least one
dimension along which we're all
oppressors and that's actually when I've
been looking at what happened in the
aftermath of the Russian Revolution that
was the bloody error so to speak because
you could take virtually ever any
individual and you could find out it's
like if there's one dimension of your
identity that makes you an oppressor
that trumps all the elements of your
identity where you're a victim and the
problem with that is there is one
element of your identity where you're an
oppressor and so that's sufficient
justification to throw you in with the
Predators
and do whatever is necessary to dispense
with you and that is exactly what
happened in the aftermath while not only
of the Russian Revolution but all of
these radical leftist revolutions it's
like well if you're a socialist while
you're not sufficiently pure from a
doctrinaire perspective and if you're a
student well then you're part of the
emerging burgeois class and if your
parents were reasonably what would you
say efficient farmers then you're part
of the kulaks and like it just went on
and on and on and on there wasn't
anybody who escaped from the from being
tarred with the brush of oppressor and
that's because that is because each of
us are in fact oppressors and oppressed
every single person shares both of those
things in common so um got a couple of
minutes left so this might be quite a
big question but just come back from the
US where we interview Paul van der
play Christian pastor who's been doing
quite a lot of videos about your your
thought he one of his questions was he
says he he sees a real sort of stoicism
in your thought so pick up your cross
and drag it up the hill his question is
what's at the top of the hill he said
here thought well that's because he
hasn't listened to the times when I've
been talking about it I guess because
I've said it repeatedly you stumble
uphill with your burden towards the City
of God that's the that's the story does
that mean the City of God do you I would
say that that's that's a place where
everyone bears maximum responsibility
and speaks the truth that's what it is
and what's the responsibility you're
responsible for the suffering in the
world you're responsible for the
malevolence in the world and you're
responsible for the veracity of your
utter insanity of God you're maximally
responsible for the suffering you're
maximally responsible for the
malevolence and you speak the truth
that's what it is very concise so you
can tell paul van der clay that that's
great
Jordan thank you very much my pleasure
nice to see you again
you
[Music]